# Shwetha Rajaram

shwethar@umich.edu shwetharajaram.github.io University of Michigan, Ann Arbor School of Information

#### Overview

I study how we can design safer and more privacy-friendly augmented and virtual reality experiences. To do so, I develop novel interactive systems that allow me to investigate the implications of using AR/VR in various application areas and explore methods for integrating privacy guidelines in AR/VR practitioners' workflows.

Research interests: human-computer interaction, AR/VR, privacy & security

#### Education

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

SEPT 2020 - present

Ph.D. in Information

Advisor: Prof. Michael Nebeling

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

SEPT 2015 - MAY 2019

CHI 2020

B.S.E. in Computer Science & Engineering

### **Publications**

#### Peer-Reviewed Full Papers

Michael Nebeling, Shwetha Rajaram, Liwei Wu, Yifei Cheng, Jaylin Herskovitz. CHI 2021 XRStudio: A Virtual Production and Live Streaming System for Immersive Instructional Experiences.

Michael Nebeling, Maximillian Speicher, Xizi Wang, <u>Shwetha Rajaram</u>, Brian D. Hall, Zijian Xie, Alexander R. E. Raistrick, Michelle Aebersold, Edward G. Happ, Jiayin Wang, Yanan Sun, Lotus Zhang, Leah E. Ramsier, Rhea Kulkarni.

MRAT: The Mixed Reality Analytics Toolkit. Best Paper Award

### Workshop Papers

Shwetha Rajaram, Franziska Roesner, Michael Nebeling. <i>Designing</i>
Privacy-Informed Sharing Techniques for Multi-User Augmented Reality.

VR4Sec 2021

## **Teaching Experience**

### University of Michigan, Ann Arbor

Graduate Student Instructor, SI 559: Introduction to AR/VR Application Design	SEPT 2021 - present
Instructional Aide, EECS 493: User Interface Development	JAN 2019 - MAY 2019

# **Professional Experience**

JP Morgan Chase, Jersey City, NJ	JAN - DEC 2018
Software Engineering Intern	
John Deere, Moline, IL	MAY - AUG 2017
Information Technology Intern	

### Awards

CHI 2020 Best Paper Award	MAY 2020
Society of Women Engineers Outstanding Collegiate Member	OCT 2019
MLK Spirit Award, UM College of Engineering	JAN 2019

### Service

Assistant to Program Chairs	T 2021
-----------------------------	--------

### Reviewing

IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR)	2021

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2021-2022

#### Leadership & Outreach

Washtenaw Elementary Science Olympiad (WESO)

SEP 2011 - present

**Event Supervisor** 

Society of Women Engineers (SWE) at UMich

APR 2016 - APR 2019

President, Executive Board Secretary, Executive Board Summer Engineering Exploration Camp Director Elementary Outreach Officer

Women+ Excelling More in Mathematics, Engineering and APR 2016 - present Science (F.E.M.M.E.S.)

Website Developer Capstone Activities Coordinator Volunteer

### **Academic Mentoring**

Chen Chen, University of Michigan School of Information (Masters)

JUNE 2021 - present Sereen Kallerackal, University of Michigan School of Information FEB - APR 2021 (Masters) Maya Subramanian, University of Michigan Computer Science JAN - MAR 2021 (Undergraduate) I Hun Chan, University of Michigan Computer Science JAN - MAR 2021 (Undergraduate)

#### Skills

Research Methods: HCI systems research, mixed-methods user studies), user-driven elicitation, interviews, focus groups

Programming Languages: C#, HTML/Javascript, C++, Python

AR/VR Technologies

SDKs: Unity Engine (ARFoundation, Vuforia, MRTK) and A-Frame

Devices: mobile AR, HoloLens 1/2, Oculus Rift, Windows Mixed Reality headsets

#### Coursework

#### Ph.D. Courses

Algorithms & Societal Implications, Introduction to Statistics and Data Analysis, Privacy in Information Technology, Human-Computer Interaction, Research Methods, Doctoral Foundation Seminar (*Information Science Theory*)

#### Masters in Information Courses

Developing AR/VR Experiences, Engineering Interactive Systems, Contextual Inquiry, Graphic Design, Fundamentals of Human Behavior, Game Development Research, Independent Study (AR/VR)

#### Selected Undergraduate Courses

Game Development, User Interface Development, Web Systems, Intro to Computer Security, Intro to Machine Learning, Data Structures and Algorithms, Intro to Computer Organization, Intro to Computer Science Theory, Interaction Design, Drawing